Payton E. Rodman

Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Rd, Cambridge CB3 0HA

Summary of Research Interests

My current research, supervised by Professor Christopher Reynolds, focuses on the production of strong magnetic fields via dynamo action within accretion discs around supermassive black holes, such as those found in the centres of massive galaxies. My thesis aims to investigate different field configurations and their evolution using the magnetohydrodynamical (MHD) code Athena++.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy Astronomy

Expected 2023 University of Cambridge, Cambridge UK

- · Gates Cambridge scholar
- · Supervisor: Professor Christopher Reynolds

Bachelor of Science (Hons) Physics

2018

University of Tasmania, Hobart AUS

- · Awarded first class Honours with University Medal
- · Thesis: Probing Intracluster Gas with Faraday Rotation from Black Hole Jets
- · Supervisors: Dr Stanislav Shabala, Dr Ross Turner

Bachelor of Science Physics and Applied Mathematics

2017

University of Tasmania, Hobart AUS

· GPA: 7.0/7.0

Refereed Publications

1. Radio Galaxy Zoo: observational evidence for environment as the cause of radio source asymmetry Rodman, P. E., Turner, R. J., Shabala, S. S., Banfield, J. K., Wong, O.-I., Andernach, H., Garon, A. F., Kapińska, A. D., Norris, R. P., Rudnick, L. (2019), MNRAS, 482(4):5625-5641

Research Experience

Undergraduate Vacation Scholar

Nov 2016 — Feb 2017

CSIRO Astronomy and Space Science, Perth AUS

· Supervisor: Dr Cormac Reynolds

Used large-scale, multi-epoch surveys to study variability in radio sources caused by inhomogeneities in the interstellar and intergalactic medium.

Summer Research Student

Nov 2015 — Feb 2016

University of Tasmania, Hobart, AUS

· Supervisors: Dr Stanislav Shabala, Dr Ross Turner Used data from the citizen science project Radio Galaxy Zoo to study whether nearby galaxy clustering affects the physical properties of AGN jets, with focus on classical double radio galaxies.

Awards, Prizes, and Scholarships

Awaras, Frizes, and Schotarships	
· University Medal (UTAS)	2019
· Cambridge Australia Scholarship (Cambridge; Honorary)	2019
Gates Cambridge Scholarship (Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation)	2019
Dean's Honour Roll (UTAS)	2018, 2017
Ken McCracken Prize (UTAS)	2018
Vice-Chancellor's Leadership Award (UTAS)	2018
Don Gaffney Scholarship (UTAS)	2018
AIP Summer Meeting Travel Scholarship (AIP)	2017
Australian Institute of Physics Prize (AIP)	2017
TEMCO Community Foundation Scholarship in Science (UTAS)	2017
Sir Phillip Fysh Prize (UTAS) CSIRO Undergraduate Vacation Scholarship (CSIRO)	2016
CSIRO Undergraduate Vacation Scholarship (CSIRO) Dean's Summer Research Scholarship (UTAS)	2016 2015
· Dean's Summer Research Scholarship (OTAS) · John Fox Memorial Prize (UTAS)	2015
• John Fox Memorial Prize (UTAS) • F.M. Young Memorial Prize (UTAS)	2015
• Dr. Peter Smith Scholarship in the Physical Sciences (UTAS)	2015
511 receir simicir seriotarismp in the ringsteat serences (61716)	2010
Department Talks	
• Cambridge Institute of Astronomy , Wednesday Seminar talk Title TBD	2021
Cambridge Institute of Astronomy, X-ray BunClub Environment as a cause of radio source asymmetry	Jan 2020
· UTAS School of Natural Sciences AGN accretion disks and X-ray variability	Sep 2019
· UTAS School of Natural Sciences	Oct 2018
Probing Intra-Cluster Gas with Faraday Rotation from Black Hole Jets	OCT 2010
· CSIRO Astronomy & Space Science , 15 Minutes of Fame The Spectral Signature of Interstellar Scintillation	Feb 2017
· UTAS School of Natural Sciences	Feb 2016
Is environment the cause of radio jet asymmetry in Active Galactic Nuclei?	
Teaching Experience	
 Supervisor (recitation sections of 3 students), Part II Astrophysical Fluid Dynamic University of Cambridge 	L ent 2020
· Marker, Statistical Physics and Solid State Physics University of Tasmania	Sem 2 2019
· Marker, Physics 1A University of Tasmania	Sem 1 2018, 2019
• Marker, Physics 1B University of Tasmania	Sem 2 2018
Peer tutor, Physics 1A	Sem 1 2017
University of Tasmania	

Technical Skills

- · Programming/scripting languages: C++, Python, Matlab, \LaTeX · Simulation suites: Athena++, Pluto

Public Outreach

· Tastrofest (1hr), invited public lectures on black holes	2017–2019
· University of Tasmania Open Days and Cub Scout Visits, regular volunteer	2016-2019
· Tasmanian Youth Science Forum Panellist	2019
· UTAS Science & Engineering Investigation Awards Head Judge	2018
· BeakerStreet@TMAG Roving Scientist	2018
· Festival of Bright Ideas Presenter	2018
· Young Tassie Scientist	2018